All right. Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So today's דף daf is
דף ה', Daf He, so for us it's פ"א, Peh Aleph, but
we pick up on the bottom of
פ' עמוד ב' Peh Amud Bet and we are looking at the
whole discussion about what constitutes a נדר עינוי נפש neder inuy nefesh
of affliction of the soul of the person actually that the husband
is entitled to annul,
and we're also going to see another category of בינו לבינה, beino
lebeinah, things that particularly relate to the interaction, the dynamic, the relationship
between the two of them. And we pick up
with ורמי דרבי יוסי אדרבי יוסי, V'rammi d'Rabbi Yosi ad d'Rabbi Yosi,
eight lines from the bottom on פ' עמוד ב'. Peh Amud Bet.
פ' עמוד ב', Peh Amud Bet, 80b, it should be the top
page you've got there. No? Yes, eight lines from the bottom. ורמי
דרבי יוסי אדרבי יוסי.
V'rammi d'Rabbi Yosi ad
d'Rabbi Yosi. Okay, so ורמי דרבי יוסי אדרבי יוסי V'rammi d'Rabbi Yosi
ad d'Rabbi Yosi and we showed a contradiction of the two Rabbi
Yosis, because Rabbi Yosi in our משנה mishna says that not bathing
is not considered to be an issue of עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh.
Let's see how that plays out. And here's the ברייתא braiysa that
we have, this is actually a תוספתא tosefta in בבא מציעא Bava
Metzia I believe. And here's what it says. Okay, ורמי דרבי יוסי
אדרבי יוסי, V'rammi d'Rabbi Yosi ad d'Rabbi Yosi, because here's what we
say.
מעיין שבני העיר, Ma'ayan shebnei ha'ir, a wellspring of the people of
the city.
You've got one city, actually עיר ir is a village.
You have one town that has a wellspring and you have another
town that doesn't have the wellspring. So חייהם וחיי אחרים, chayeihem v'chayei
acheirim, the life of those in the town that has the wellspring
and the life of the other town. If they have to choose
between their life and the life of the other town, do they
keep the water for themselves, do they give it to the other
town? So that's like a no-brainer.
חייהם קודמין, Chayeihem kodmin, take your גמרא Gemara or you have a
package of pages there because we're dispossessing them. Okay, so חייהם קודמין,
chayeihem kodmin, their lives come first לחיי אחרים, l'chayei acheirim, to the
lives of
others, which just makes
sense. בהמתן ובהמת אחרים, Behemtan u'vehemt acheirim, בהמתן קודמת behemtan kodemes for
בהמת אחרים. behemt acheirim. There's no, the office is not available today,
so the גמרא Gemara drops off the pages. Okay, so you have
a wellspring of one town, their lives come before the lives of
the other town, they get to keep the water for themselves, that's
pretty obvious, that's the general principle in all of הלכה halacha which
is וחי אחיך עמך, v'chai achicha imach, חייך קודמין לחיי אחיך, chayecha
kodmin l'chayei achicha, your life, you know, comes before somebody else's, you
have a primary responsibility to take care of yourself. You can't go
into that room, Joe, Joe, you can't go in, they're locking you.
I'll help you with the chair. Oh, the chair, okay.
All right, sorry. All right, back to this. Okay, בהמתן
ובהמת אחרים, behemtan u'vehemt acheirim, בהמתן קודמת לבהמת אחרים. behemtan kodemes l'vehemt
acheirim. Now let's say both towns have enough water for themselves, but
because of this wellspring there's the first town, you know, can provide
for their animals and the second town cannot provide for their animals.
Same story, it's your wellspring, your animals come before the other town's
animals. כביסתן וכביסת
אחרים. Kvisasan u'kvisas acheirim. Now, both towns have enough water to provide
for their animals and for the people, but they don't have, wait
a second, but they don't have enough water to provide for laundry,
only the first town with the wellspring can provide for their laundry.
So guess what? Same obvious point. כביסתן קודמת לכביסת אחרים, Kvisasan kodemes
l'kvisas acheirim,
their water, the use, their laundry, the need of their laundry comes
before the laundry of the other town, they keep the water from
the wellspring for themselves. All of that is very obvious, your responsibility
towards yourself comes before your responsibility towards others. Now here comes the
kicker. חיי אחרים וכביסתן. Chayei acheirim u'kvisasan. Okay, basically it's between the
lives of the people in the other town or do they give
the water to the other town so the other town can use
it for, you know, because basically they need it for basic sustenance,
they don't have enough water basically for the people, or do they
say no, we have our laundry to do, so therefore we're not
going to give it to you, we need to use the water
for our laundry. So the ברייתא braiysa says,
חיי
אחרים קודמין לכביסתן. chayei acheirim kodmin l'kvisasan. So that's the obvious answer,
you got to give the water to the next town, right, their
need for doing it for their basic, you know, life sustaining purposes
comes before your need for the water for the laundry, even if
it's your water or the wellspring at least starts in your town.
רבי יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yosi omer, Rabbi Yosi says no, כביסתן קודמת
לחיי אחרים. kvisasan kodemes l'chayei acheirim.
Your laundry gets to come before their lives if it's your water.
So by the way, I have to tell you, I was once
in somebody's house, a rabbi I know in Boston, and I was,
you know, they put me in the guest room which was right
near the laundry room, and as I was walking by the laundry
room I saw they had a little sign up in the laundry
room that says כביסתן קודמת לחיי אחרים. kvisasan kodemes l'chayei acheirim. But
anyway. But anyway,
so this is crazy, right? What could this mean that, before we
even get to where the איזביצר Izhbitzer brings this out, what could
this mean? Somebody else there is... No, possibly literally.
Yeah, but that doesn't even matter right now. Somebody else is dying
in the next town and they need water, that means they have
water, water, I need water. So, I'm sorry, I gotta do my
laundry.
So the תוספות Tosfos reads this that it doesn't literally mean they're
not going to get the water. He says the key here is
the word קודמת kodemet and the way he understands it is, this
is a natural wellspring, you know, and it basically flows from town
A to town B. And town A basically has put up some
type of a dam or something in order that they can use
the water for something, and only after like they're done using the
water do they let it continue to flow. I don't know exactly
the hydrophysics or whatever,
but basically קודמת kodemet just means we're allowed to first, you know,
take the water, you know, stop and have pause the water and
take it and use it for our laundry, you know, maybe dam
it up so that we can all collect and we can all
do the laundry or whatever, and then afterwards it'll go on to
your town. We're allowed to come first because it comes from our
town first. Now, if you say that, it's not like a big
deal because eventually everybody's going to get it, and he's obviously framing
it that way so the assumption is that nobody's going to die
in the next town as a result. It's just that, okay, I
know you need it, but you wait another hour for a drink.
It starts in our town, we get to do our laundry first,
okay, even though you're thirsty. All right, so it's not a big
חידוש, chiddush, it's just a question of order, but no, there's no
lasting consequence. The ר"ן Ran seems to prefer to interpret it literally.
And it's again extremely hard to understand, you know, people will say
something like, well, look, if it's a part of the principle of
וחי אחיך עמך, vechai achicha imach, חייך קודמים, chayecha kodmim, your life.
So does your life literally mean your life? I mean, let me
ask you another question. There's a question that's asked by one of
the ראשונים Rishonim that plays a big role, you know, in terms
of issues of like organ transplant, live organ transplant. Do I have
to risk my limb to save somebody else's life? Right? Or let's
say I will definitely lose a limb, but I'll definitely save a
life. So obviously, his life is a bigger thing than my limb,
right? And nevertheless, the פסק הלכה psak halacha is no, הלכה, Halacha,
תורה Torah doesn't make that demand, that type of a sacrifice from
you, right? Even though obviously a life is more important than a
limb, you are allowed to first put your own needs first, you
know, even, you know, even and you don't have to just do
this type of quantitative, you know, type of a trade-off. So even
your limb comes before their life. So for their lives. Okay, so
now you could logically take it the next step and say, well
look, you know, maybe, you know, having TV and buying my iPods
or whatever, that doesn't come before somebody else's life, but something that's
like directly about, I don't know, my body, you know, the clothes
that I wear, something that's like central to my state of well-being,
you know, maybe that... maybe I'm allowed to put them before... No,
that's very harsh. I can imagine two people walking in the desert
and remember this, no, I gotta do my laundry, I'm sorry buddy,
you know, but they're not exactly walking in the desert, like this
is, you know, somebody like a little bit distant. And again, it
sounds crazy, and I'm not sort of endorsing it, but you know,
this is like part of the critique that who was that crazy
ethicist Peter Singer? Yeah, makes. Like he says, if you think about
it, we do it every single day. You know, we spend whatever
it is $200 or $500 on an iPod, you know, there are
like ten lives in developing countries or more, a hundred lives we
could save if we would write out that check. And every single
day we decide to spend money on our own like trivial stuff,
you go out one night to dinner, you spend $200 on a
dinner, you know, rather than saving lives with it. You're always sort
of making that calculation, because it's very abstract, there's somebody out there
somewhere that could be helped or whatever. You know, so now it's
a little different here because it's not so abstract, it's not that
there's somebody in some other place in the world that could be
helped, right? A, they're fellow Jews, which creates a particular sense of
responsibility, B, they seem to be just one town over, you know,
so it might be that somewhere else across the globe it might
be a different story. And we know, whenever there was an issue
with Jews like taken captive, פדיון שבויים, pidyon shvuyim, you know, people
would sacrifice significant, you know, well-being in order to, you know, because
of that sense of responsibility. So, you know, we just doesn't really
help, we don't פוסקין pasken this way, certainly not in its literal
sense, but it's worth thinking about might he actually mean it like
literally to some degree.
Yeah. Is there a way to read חיי chayay as like activities
of life as opposed to... does he have to read it literally
because if it's not...
Right, so some read it that way as well, that חיי אחיך
chayei achicha again doesn't mean they'll die if they don't have water.
It means
they have enough water to live on, but they don't have enough
water so, you know, their life is difficult, right, but it doesn't
mean... right, exactly, their well-being but not literally life. Exactly. But the
lowest part would be life. There are ways of toning this down,
but you know, and I certainly don't think it means literally that
people in the next town are dying and you would say, I'm
sorry, I need to... But it is interesting in thinking about how,
in our contemporary, we do sometimes focus on a high state of
well-being for ourselves and we're not always prioritize much more basic needs
of others. Wellness
and sense of human life.
Right. Right, exactly.
Well that's a good point too. I'll say one other point and
then I'll take the question, which is,
in issues of צדקה Tzedakah there are there's a hierarchy and there
really is, and most people don't stop to realize this, two different
sort of metrics or hierarchies. One we say ענייך ועניי עירך ענייך
קודמים, Aniucha ve'aniyei ircha, aniucha kodmim, your poor and the poor of
the neighboring city, your poor comes first. And the other thing we
say
is עני ועשיר עני קודם, Ani ve'ashir, ani kodem, whether they give
money to a poor person or a rich person for some reason
needs a loan or whatever, the poor person comes first. Now those
are two different issues. One is a measurement of degree of proximity,
how close they are geographically, relationship, your family, somebody else's family and
so on, different ways of measuring proximity. And the other is degree
of need. So what happens when they're in competition? Let's say the
poor in my city need education, but the poor in the neighboring
city need clothes,
which comes before education. Where's my primary responsibility? The poor in my
city or the poor in the neighboring city? So this is like
not clear in the גמרא Gemara whether which comes first, proximity or
need. And the חתם סופר Chasam Sofer says need always comes first,
that you first have to make sure that all the poor everywhere
in the world have their basic needs. Then you get up to
the next level of need and you start with your city and
then you make every and then you get to the, but it's
always need comes first. Others, like the ערוך השולחן, Aruch Hashulchan, seem
to emphasize
that your primary responsibility is always with those that are in your
city or closest to you. You have some responsibility to those more
distant. To some degree, that's part of what's going on here. Again,
we don't want to imagine that the people in the next city
are dying, but nevertheless you could say my laundry comes before the
next town's
education, the next town's providing a certain greater level of well-being for
that next town. So really important questions here in terms of thinking
about these issues about priorities in צדקה Tzedakah and so on. Yes?
Is it the town that has the water source wants to use
it for agriculture and they say well we need it because we
have to
eat?
Right, meaning where, if we need it for our, well that's exactly
the issue here.
So laundry's different than food, right?
If the first town needs it for food, then that would probably
be more like חייהם, Chayeihem, that would be like
the stream going from one town to the other, it's not a
permanent thing.
Exactly, exactly.
So that's why תוספות Tosafot reads it as a question of who
gets first, not that one is getting and the other isn't getting.
It's just a question of who gets to stand in line first
for what purposes. Okay, so that was like that's a really fascinating
תוספות Tosafot and it's not discussed in the גמרא Gemara at all
except for to tell us that look how important רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi thinks laundry is. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi thinks your laundry comes
before their חייהם, Chayeihem, whatever that means, life or
well-being, and nevertheless רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says that if you take
a נדר, Neder, a woman takes a נדר Neder about not bathing,
that's not considered to be עינוי נפש. Inuy nefesh. Okay, so how
could not bathing not be עינוי נפש Inuy nefesh and laundry be
on such a high level in the priority list? So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, השתא, Hashta, now, כביסה, Kvisa, when it comes
to laundry, אמר רבי יוסי יש בהם צער, Amar Rabbi Yosi yesh
bahem tzar, that there's
real discomfort, גוף כולו, Guf kulo, the entire body of not bathing,
לא כל שכן, Lo kol sheken, how much more so would that
be true? So the גמרא Gemara says how could that be? How
could רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi heighten the importance of laundry and still
have a low value of the importance of bathing? So the
גמרא Gemara says אמרי אין הכי איתא לרבי יוסי, Amri in hachi
ita leRabbi Yosi, כביסה Kvisa is very weighty for רבי יוסי, Rabbi
Yosi, דאמר שמואל, De'amar Shmuel, because שמואל Shmuel says, here's the גמרא's
Gemara sort of medical statement,
האי ארבוביתא דרישא, Hai arvuvita dereisha, that sort of האי ארבוביתא Hai
arvuvita is like the filth or when
all the hair on your head is like sort of tangled, the
tangling, the dirt and tangling of the hair of the head, meaning
of your hair if you don't wash your hair, מתיא
לידי עוירא, Mayti lidei avira, that brings about blindness. ארבוביתא דמאני, Arvuvita
demani, if you have like the filth of your garments, you don't
launder your garments, מתיא לידי שעמימותא, Mayti lidei sha'amimuta, that brings to
a type of dumbfoundedness like a type of some type of a
psychological state that's not exactly the same
as שטות, Shtut, but
but some type of a not mental well-being.
ארבוביתא דגופא, Arvuvita degufa, if you have these sort of filth of
the body, you don't bathe, מתיא לידי שיחני וכיבי, Mayti lidei shichney
vekivi, that brings about like sores and blisters. So the גמרא Gemara
says... It's worse, what would you rather have? Sores and blisters of
that is less bad than the not right mind. Well be either
way though, either way it's pretty bad. I mean if it brings
sores and blisters then how could רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi say it's
not עינוי נפש? inui nefesh? I don't know.
But the second one I wouldn't say is causal, but it could
be an effect.
Like somebody why are you not
bathing because you're just that disheveled that that reflects?
Oh that's an interesting point. Somebody who goes around like that might
it's probably oh that's I'm not sure that's how the גמרא Gemara
meant, but that's a nice מחשבה. mahshava. Okay. So anyway yeah it's
still a little strange, right? Because nevertheless like they're both pretty bad.
Right? The גמרא Gemara is saying like, okay, it's possible רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi thinks not laundering look, the other way to say it
is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi thinks that you don't need much of
a reason to keep the water for yourself, it's your water, any
reason might be good enough to keep the water for yourself but
that doesn't mean that we're going to call it עינוי נפש. inui
nefesh. Alright. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: שלחו
מתם, Shalchu mitam, they sent from there from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
הזהרו
בארבוביתא, Hizahru b'arvuvsa, be careful with ארבוביתא, arvuvsa, with the not bathing,
you know, with the filth that comes through apparently not bathing or
not laundering. הזהרו בחבורה, Hizahru b'chabura, be careful of meaning to be
a good thing to have like a sense of like community or
חבורה chabura here as explained by the ראשונים Rishonim to mean to
mean basically learning in חברותא chavruta is how they explain it. Now
the reason they bring in the idea of learning, you know, it
comes from the third statement here: הזהרו בבני עניים, Hizahru bivnei aniyim,
be careful take, you know, good care of the children of the
poor people who normally maybe don't even have the funds to educate
their kids. But as we were talking
about a little earlier, education?
Yeah exactly. But you really need to sort of as a community
has to take care of them, שמהם תצא תורה, shemehem taitzei Torah,
that from them ultimately will תורה Torah come, not from the wealthy
people who are whatever sending their kids to all the Ivy League
colleges, but it's the hard immigrant children that work harder, that's actually
what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. But if you're poor
and you don't come from a privileged background, you have a stronger
work ethic and you're going to work harder to get ahead and
you take your opportunity to learn as a real gift and you
take it seriously, so you have to really protect, you know, protect
them. It also might be why it speaks about this ארבוביתא, arvuvsa,
meaning like make sure that even the people that are poor in
your city have the basic ability to, you know, to bathe and
launder their clothing and take care of themselves and so on. Okay.
And בבני עניים שמהם תצא תורה, bivnei aniyim shemehem taitzei Torah, from
them תורה Torah will go out. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the verse says,
יזל מים מדליו, yizal mayim midalyav, water will flow from his from
his buckets but here the reading is מדליו, midalyav, דל dal is
also from the lowly and water is תורה. Torah. So תורה Torah
will flow from those who are the poor and the lowly. שמהם
תצא תורה יזל מים מדליו שמהם תצא תורה. shemehem taitzei Torah yizal
mayim midalyav shemehem taitzei Torah. So so from them will תורה Torah
come. ומפני מה אינם מצויין תלמידי חכמים לצאת תלמידי חכמים מבניהן? Umipnei
mah einam metzuyin talmidei chachamim l'taitzei talmidei chachamim mibeineihen? And why is
it so besides that the wealthy that are privileged maybe don't work
hard enough, again, like very global statements, but anyway that's the גמרא's
Gemara point, you know, you know,
but nevertheless besides the wealthy, the privileged, what about תלמידי חכמים? talmidei
chachamim? Why do we not see that the children of תלמידי חכמים
talmidei chachamim are also big תלמידי חכמים? talmidei chachamim? Logically you would
expect that. They prioritize learning, תורה's Torah spoken in the house. Now
some could question that observation. You know, I mean my God look
at רש"י's Rashi family. Look at רש"י's Rashi family. You know you
had רש"י Rashi and רשב"ם Rashbam and רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam and
the ר"י Ri with the next generation whatever. But you do have
like these rabbinic dynasties that are not only dynasties in the sense
of power and status but actually, you know, תורה Torah does get
passed down, either because of the genes or because of the culture
or whatever. But anyway the גמרא Gemara was saying like we don't
always see that happening. Why does that not happen though? So אמר
רב יוסף: amar Rav Yosef: שלא יאמרו תורה ירושה היא להם. shelo
yomru Torah yerusha hi lahem. It's sort of like so they shouldn't
say, meaning God made makes it happen that it that it shouldn't
happen so then the family would wind up feeling like we have
a, you know, you know, we have a possession of תורה. Torah.
It's our which even means like, A: we're not going to work
so hard, right? Yeah, my father was a תלמיד, talmid, my grandfather
was a תלמיד, talmid, my father was a תלמיד, talmid, I don't
have to work so hard. It's like what's a ירושה? yerusha? ירושה
yerusha is something that comes without any work. Right? It just gets
passed on by the previous generation. So that's why it's by contrast
to the בני עניים, bnei aniyim, בני עניים bnei aniyim they get
nothing for free. They have to work hard, right? So if you're,
you know, so maybe you don't do this so you don't take
your תורה Torah learning too easily. But it could also be not
just you've become you know, you could also be it another way,
because they feel that ירושה היא להם, yerusha hi lahem, you know,
that's why they're not work working as hard. And also not just
to explain why the kids aren't working as hard to become תלמידי
חכמים, talmidei chachamim, but like God doesn't want one family to feel
that they've got, you know, God arranges it this way as it
were so that one family doesn't feel that they have like, you
know, a monopoly on תורה. Torah. Okay. Although ירושה yerusha doesn't emphasize
the idea of monopoly as much as something you get without working
for it. רב ששת בריה דרב אידי... Rav Sheshet brei deRav Idi...
Rav Sheshet says, כדי שלא יתגדרו על הציבור, k'dei shelo yitgadru al
hatzibur, that they should not, this seems to be more the point,
the second point I was making, that they should not sort of
make themselves up over elevated over the ציבור, tzibur, haughty over the
ציבור, tzibur, like we are the family of Torah, we're the family
with all the sort of power. Yet יתגדרו, yitgadru, יתגברו, yitgabru, there's
a question or יתגאו, yitga'u, there's questions about exactly what the גרסא
girsa is. But everybody agrees that that's the sense.
Has nothing to do with making a fence like a גדר?
gader? Maybe, a fence around them and their תורה Torah and away
from the ציבור, tzibur, that could be. Like we, like it's all
ours, we have a monopoly, we're better than everybody, we're the ones
with the תורה Torah and so on. Okay.
I don't know how the חסידיק Chassidic dynasties deal with all of
this. Anyway, okay, יתגדרו, yitgadru, יתגברו yitgabru על הציבור. al hatzibur. מר
זוטרא Mar Zutra says, but I do want to say something really
important about this, which is, one of the points that I've made
in many different contexts, of like תורה Torah in contrast to the
sort of בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash as the center of
קדושה kedusha for Judaism post the חורבן, churban, is that בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash is very hierarchical, right? Only you need to be close
to it to have access, only certain people have access, כהנים, kohanim,
it has to be a dynasty, really is a ירושה, yerusha, right?
You know, that גמרא, Gemara, שלושה כתרים נכתרו לישראל, shlosha k'tarim necht'ru
l'Yisrael, כהונה kehunah is only for בני אהרן. bnei Aharon. תורה, Torah,
right, the שלושה כתרים shlosha k'tarim is, כל הרוצה יבוא ויטול, kol
harotzeh yavo v'yitol, it's completely
universal. חז"ל Chazal invented universal
education, okay, only just for the boys. Anyway, but the point is
fundamentally it's completely accessible to all, non-hierarchical, the story about הלל Hillel
falling asleep on the roof and you're poor and everybody should have
access, right? So this is really like sort of saying, we want
to make sure it doesn't become something that's the issue of a
dynasty and protected and centralized power. בני עניים bnei aniyim are the
ones that ultimately are the ones to focus on. So it's really
like being sensitive that even something that should be as universally accessible
as תורה Torah does not become something that becomes protected and hierarchical.
Okay, so that's יתגדרו על הציבור. yitgadru al hatzibur. מר זוטרא אומר
מפני שהן מתגברים על הציבור,
Mar Zutra omer mipnei
shehen mitgabrim al hatzibur, יתגדרו yitgadru
meaning
it's not that it should have become this way, it's a punishment
to them because it does become this way. When it happens that
it goes from father to son or whatever and you're the big
רב rav of the town and תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and whatever,
this matches, this happens all the time. So as a sort of
punishment as opposed to as a preventative thing, that's why it works
out that God doesn't allow it to continue to happen because
it's recompense for this. Okay. ורב אשי אמר v'Rav Ashi amar משום
דקרו לאינשי חמרי, mishum d'karu l'inshei chamrei,
because they call basically they call people donkeys. How many תלמידי חכמים?
talmidei chachamim? The תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim call the laypeople, if they
see that they and their families are the ones that have תורה
Torah and they think like yeah everybody else they're just a bunch
of עם הארץ am ha'aretz and ignoramuses and we're the only ones
that are intellectual and know things, and it leads to them, I
mean even if they don't sort of wield their power over the
ציבור, tzibur, it leads to them to look at themselves in a
very haughty way and everybody else around them.
Doesn't some גמרא Gemara already do that anyway, even if it isn't
a dynasty?
עם הארץ הדומה כבהמה,
am
ha'aretz hadomeh k'veheimah,
which is like an animal. Right, but who needs to encourage that?
Okay.
And the מהרש"א Maharsha makes a nice sharp point. He says because
if it all
runs through your family, you're going to think that there's something innate
about you and everybody else. So it's sort of very innately they
are at a lower level than you are because only your family
is able to have תורה Torah and they can't, so they must
be idiots and donkeys and whatever and it's a natural state.
Let me give some context to the תורה.
Torah. It became a digression
because they sent three things from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and one
of them was be careful with בני עניים bnei aniyim because from
them תורה Torah goes out. So it's a digression.
מים מן התורה. mayim min ha-Torah.
Well, that's also true. Right. That's also true. Maybe you're right, I
hadn't thought about that but it's about protecting the water and keeping
the water for yourself as opposed to letting the water flow to
the next town. Right, hadn't thought about that. That's a very good
point. Okay. Anyway, so okay, where was
I? רבינא אומר שאין מברכין
בתורה תחילה, Ravina omer she'ein mivarchin baTorah techila,
because they don't make a ברכה bracha before learning תורה. Torah. Now
where did that come from? That's first, that must go to the
famous גמרא. Gemara.
Because they don't really need to, right?
Maybe. Okay, so let's get back to it. דאמר רב יהודה אמר
רב, d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's meant
by the verse, מי האיש החכם ויבן את זאת, mi ha-ish ha-chacham
v'yaven et zot, who is the wise person who will understand it?
דבר זה, davar zeh, so
it's like nobody could understand it. And the
end of the פסוק pasuk is על מה אבדה הארץ, al mah
avdah ha'aretz, why was the land lost, wasted? על עזבם את תורתי,
al azvam et Torati, because they abandoned my Torah ולא הלכו בה,
v'lo halchu bah, they didn't travel in it. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, sounds like nobody could find the right answer, so
the גמרא Gemara says דבר זה... davar zeh... נשאל לחכמים, nishal lachachamim,
it was asked to the sage, ולנביאים, uleneviim, and to the prophets,
ולא פירשוהו, velo pirshuhu, and nobody was able to explain it, עד
שפירשו הקדוש ברוך הוא בעצמו ad shepirsho hakadosh baruch hu be'atzmo until
God said, דכתיב, dechativ, ויאמר השם. Vayomer Hashem. Nobody could answer until
God came along and said על עזבם את תורתי, al azvum es
torasi,
ולא הלכו בה. velo halchu bah.
I think the פסוק pasuk here, it has the full פסוק. pasuk.
ויאמר השם על עזבם את תורתי אשר נתתי לפניהם ולא שמעו בקולי
ולא הלכו בה. Vayomer Hashem al azvum es torasi asher nasati lifneihem
velo sham'u bekoli velo halchu bah.
They didn't listen to my voice and they didn't go into the
Torah. So what is this repetition? So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: היינו ולא שמעו בקולי היינו ולא הלכו בה. hainu velo sham'u
bekoli hainu velo halchu bah. Not listening to my voice seems to
be the same as not going in the path of the Torah.
So what does this double language mean? So אמר רב יהודה אמר
רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, שאין מברכין בתורה תחילה. she'ein mevorchin
batorah techila. So it means that they didn't listen to my voice
means that they didn't make the ברכה bracha on the Torah. Now
how do you get from not listening to my voice and abandoning
the Torah to not making the ברכה, bracha, and what does this
have to do with why the problem of a family that Torah
goes from, you know, father to son? So it seems to me
that, you know, Michael said what I think was the first thing
that occurred to me which was like basically that they, well, I'm
not sure which one he said, but anyway you could say that
it means that they don't like treasure it, they don't value it.
You know a ברכה bracha is sort of recognizing that it's from
God, you know, and they just sort of, you know, take it
as something that they don't hold in that type of high esteem
and that opportunity. But I think there's another point to it which
is that the ברכה bracha is not just indicating the esteem that
we hold it but it's actually saying אשר קידשנו במצוותיו וציוונו. asher
kideshanu bemitzvotav vetzivanu. It's
sort of recognizing right that this is something that
is
like, you know, we're doing because God commanded it to us. We're
doing
because, you know, because it's like it's something that we're doing for
God. ולא שמעו בקולי, velo sham'u bekoli, did you listen to my
voice? If you're not making the ברכה, bracha, you're not listening. Like,
what's the challenge that I have, anybody has that's in the profession
of the Torah profession is like, you know, when you're learning גמרא
Gemara the night before for the דף יומי daf yomi or for
something. For דף יומי daf yomi it's less this way because I
don't get paid for it, but anyway it's like am I just,
am I preparing for my job the next day or am I
learning Torah, right? So
if it's all your whole life and it's your family and this
is what you do and this is your whole, you know, goes
father to son to son or whatever, then it could be that
this is just, you know, this is our business. Torah is our
family business, right? So if it's our family business we're not making
a ברכה. bracha. You know this is what, this is what we
do. This is how, this is who, you know, our פרנסה, parnasa,
this is our life, this is our, and so on. So I
think that that's partly the point that it says that like you
lose the sense of treasuring it, you lose the sense that you're
doing it because God said, because it's a מצווה mitzvah to do
it, and it just becomes like, you know, part of your, you
know, the stuff that you do every day and the stuff that
your family does and, you know, your family business.
Maybe that's also why you're not supposed to get שכר sachar for
teaching Torah, right?
That's, yeah, that's correct. That's true for every מצווה, mitzvah, but that's
also correct. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like
this,
אלריי. Alright. Now we get back to discussing about bathing and whether
it's עינוי נפש, inoui nefesh, but that was a fun digression.
Okay. So אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav.
Oh, we did that.
איסי בר יהודה Isi bar Yehuda לא אתא למתיבתא lo asa lemesivta
דרבי יוסי deRabbi Yosi תלתא יומי tlata yomei for three days. אשכחי
ורדימוס בר רבי יוסי. ashkachi Vardimus bar Rabbi Yosi. Vardimus who was
רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yosi son, interesting name right, we've never heard of
ורדימוס בר רבי יוסי, Vardimus bar Rabbi Yosi, never in like a,
yeah, rose, I don't know, also maybe it was a Greek name.
Anyway, אמר ליה, amar leh, מאי טעמא לא אתית לבי מדרשא דאבא?
mai ta'ama lo asis levei midrasha de'abba? Why didn't you come to
my father's בית מדרש Beis Medrash תלתא יומי tlata yomei for three
days? אמר ליה, amar leh, כי טעמיה דאבוך לא ידענא היכי אתינא.
ki ta'ameh de'avuch lo yad'ana heichi asina. If I don't understand what
your father's talking about, how should I come to the
בית מדרש? Beis Medrash? אמר ליה, amar leh, לימא מר מאי קאמר
ליה דלא ידעת טעמיה. leima mar mai ka'amar leh dela yadata ta'ameh.
Tell me what my father said to you that you couldn't understand.
דלמא ידענא טעמיה, dilma yad'ana ta'ameh, maybe I could explain the reason.
אמר ליה, amar leh, הדר תנא hadar tana what he taught. רבי
יוסי אומר כביסתן קודמת לחיי אחרים. Rabbi Yosi omer kvisatan kodemet lechayei
acherim. So the laundry comes before other people's life as we read,
we said that's absurd if you read that literally. I don't know
what your father's talking about. So how can I keep on going
to the בית מדרש? Beis Medrash? He says these things make no
sense. So קרא מנלן, kra minalan, where could you get, where do
you get this from? What's a פסוק pasuk that indicates it? אמר
ליה, amar leh, דכתיב dechativ because the פסוק pasuk said, ומגרשיהם יהיו
לבהמתם ולכל חייתם. umigrashieihem yihyu livhemtam ulechol chayasam. Right there sort of
the suburbs, the areas, the fields outside the cities of the לוויים
Leviim will be for their animals and for all of their חייתם
chayasam לכל חייתם. lechol chayasam. So מאי חייתם? mai chayasam? What does
חייתם chayasam mean? אילימא חיה, ilima chaya, if it means their wild
animals, the deer or whatever, הלא חיה בכלל בהמה, halo chaya bichlal
behema, that was included in
בהמתם. behemtam. אלא מאי חייתם? ki ela mai chayasam? חיותא ממש. chayusa
mamash. So what does it mean חייתם? chayasam? Things that literally sustain
life. פשיטא, pishita, of course they can use it for that. אלא
לאו כביסה, ela lav kvisah, it must mean that it's laundry. Coming
to include even something like laundry. דאיכא צערא דגיבשושא, De'ika tzaar degivshusa,
if you don't do laundry you have all of the accoutrements that
the גמרא Gemara mentioned before that come from the filth, etc. and
therefore what? So what does that prove? That they use their fields
for laundry. וחייה. V'chaya. So to me it shows that right, laundry,
somehow, of course it's like one of these things of עיקר חסר
מן הספר. Ikar chaser min hasefer. The Torah isn't talking about laundry,
the Torah talks about חייתם. Chayasam. So first we have חייתם Chayasam
to mean life, not animals, and then we say and that must
mean therefore something that's not literally life, because that would have been
obvious, it must mean something that comes after בהמה Behema because remember
the order came, your life, your בהמה, Behema, and then it went
to laundry, right? Remember that in the order of what you use
the water for? Right? So if it's not בהמה, Behema, we've already
covered בהמה, Behema, what's next on the list of things that are
important, it must be laundry, and it's included in the word חיה.
Chaya. But how do you know it's someone else's? I don't know,
but once you get to call it your life, at least you
can start saying that it might come before your life.
There's a lot of diseases that are
transmitted from sewage and E. coli and stuff and whatever, typhus.
Oh, that's an excellent point. It's central to health. Right, because of,
yeah, that's an excellent point, you got some diseases without laundering clothes.
Yeah.
Okay. So, animal comes from the Latin anima.
Which is?
Like life.
חיה. Chaya. Oh, that's interesting. Okay. Alright, now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosei, אין אלו נדרי עינוי
נפש. Ein elu nidrei inui nefesh. Back to the point that he
says, not bathing and not putting on makeup is not considered עינוי
נפש. Inui nefesh. So the husband cannot annul based on his power
to annul things of עינוי נפש. Inui nefesh. But we'll be reminded
that he also has power to annul things that are בין לו
לבינה, Bein lo l'veina, that are between the two of them, that
might not be binding
if he winds up marrying another guy, but anyway, so that would
be one halakhic difference, but
nevertheless he can still annul. So the גמרא Gemara has the following
question, איבעיא להו, Ibaia lehu, they raised the following question. רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yosei, מהו שיפר משום דברים שבינו לבינה? Mahu sheyafer mishum devarim
shebeino l'veina?
Fine, bathing and makeup is not considered עינוי נפש Inui nefesh for
her, if it's just about her own physical state. But certainly, if
like the husband might like her to, you know, be bathed and
every now and then put on makeup to, you know, so does
that affect their relationship? And is he able to annul it from
that perspective? תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. אמר רבי יוסי,
Amar Rabbi Yosei, אין אלו נדרי עינוי נפש. Ein elu nidrei inui
nefesh. These are not נדרים Nedarim of עינוי נפש. Inui nefesh. So
it sounds like he doesn't just say he can't be מיפר. Meifer.
He seems like it doesn't go into the category of עינוי נפש.
Inui nefesh. Not like it's impossible for him to be מיפר. Meifer.
So that's what the גמרא Gemara tries to infer. אבל דברים שבינו
לבינה הכי נמי? Aval devarim shebeino l'veina hachi nami? But maybe, but
it sounds like they would be possibly in the category of דברים
שבינו לבינה. Devarim shebeino l'veina. גמרא Gemara says not necessarily. דילמא לדידי
קאמר. Dilma l'didi ka'amar. Maybe he's saying, this is his way of
responding to the
Rabbis. לדידי, L'didi, as far as I'm concerned, אפילו דברים שבינו לבינה
לא הוי. Afilu devarim shebeino l'veina lo havi. I don't even put
it into דברים שבינו לבינה. Devarim shebeino l'veina. I think that, you
know, the husband can tolerate it, it's not a big deal, etc.
ולדידכו, Ul'didchu, for you, דאמריתו הוי נדרי עינוי נפש, De'amritu havi nidrei
inui nefesh, you think this stuff is so important that it gets
into the category of נדרי עינוי נפש. Nidrei inui nefesh. You know
what? That's a little overboard. אודו לי דאין אלו נדרי עינוי נפש.
Odu li de'ein elu nidrei inui nefesh. You should concede to me
that it doesn't really deserve to be עינוי נפש. Inui nefesh. Maybe
I can understand your position if your position was that it was
בינו לבינה, Beino l'veina, but I don't,
calling it עינוי נפש Inui nefesh is all overboard. That might be
what he's saying. But he personally might hold that it's not even
in the בינו לבינה. Beino l'veina.
Do you think there's like an objective category?
No, it's all a question of assessing right what and the question
interestingly I think the more interesting question or maybe this is what
you meant Michael is not just how do the Rabbis decide, but
does it get to decide for all people? Or that is what
you meant. Right, that's a really good question. It does sound from
the משנה Mishnah like yes, we're making a big decision for all
people, right? On the other hand, for me, I'm an extremist and
not bathing is עינוי נפש. Inui nefesh. For you, it isn't. For
one type of a relationship, the wife might never put on makeup
and everybody loves that, and for other, who knows, every relationship is
different. But you're absolutely right. It sounds like in law we have
to put things in formal categories, right? How we know that, I
don't know.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara answers about that. Okay, מאי?
Mai?
So what's the story? רב אדא בר אהבה אומר מיפר, Rav Adda
bar Ahava omer meifer, the husband can annul, it is דברים שבינו
לבינה. Devarim shebeino l'veina. ורב הונא אמר אינו מיפר, V'Rav Huna amar
eino meifer, he cannot annul. Okay, so now what? We're not done.
Now why can he not annul? Why is it not דברים שבינו
לבינה? Devarim shebeino l'veina? שלא מצינו שועל שמת בעפר פיר. Shelo matzinu
shual shemet b'afar pir. We've never found that a fox that would
have died in the dust, the dirt of its own fox hole.
Like a bee drowned in its own honey?
Yeah, something like that. Which basically means look, I mean look, we
got to you know this whole thing is obviously you know disturbing
because on the one hand the whole ability to annul is all
about you know the husband sort of power over his wife right
and that the idea is that he's in control, he says I
don't like this. not all things, but he has that power. And
you know, the whole question about is it בינו לבינה beino l'veina
is really a question like she's going to do some thing, to
what degree does it affect him? You know, obviously it plays into
some of these classic sort of patriarchal dynamics. But this is, I'm
just sort of acknowledging that. I don't know what to say about
that, but I'm acknowledging that. You know, so here too, it's like,
I don't know what you think about this metaphor. But the point
is, is that the fox doesn't die in the dirt that he's
accustomed to. So if a man's wife doesn't bathe, you know, that's,
he's, they're used to their physical closeness and therefore if that's the
natural dirt or whatever, that's not going to, he'll tolerate it. You
know, people learn to tolerate the lives that they grow up with.
Like, you know, somebody who lives, I don't know if this is
a good analogy or not, it makes it worse. But you know,
some people sort of, you know, let their houses start, you know,
for various reasons, they're depressed or whatever, things they don't do their
dishes and they pile up in the sink and the house is
a mess and you'd say how could anybody live like this, right?
But somehow if it starts becoming like it's your environment you somehow
figure out a way to live like this. So like yeah people
learn to tolerate people learn to live with a lot of things
that are part of their environment.
Yeah but until then, in other words, let's say she started out
the marriage, they're newly married, she bathes, and then you know like
a week later I'm not bathing again.
Right exactly. I don't know, yes good point. Okay anyway so that's
this. Now תניא כוותיה דרבא בר אבא, Tanya k'vattei d'Rava bar Abba,
we look like תניא כוותיה דרבא בר אבא Tanya k'vattei d'Rava bar
Abba that it remains in this דברים שבינו לבינה devarim she-beino le-veina
category.
What does it teach? דברים שיש בהן עינוי נפש מיפר בין בינו
לבינה בין בינו לבינה ואחרים. devarim she-yesh ba-hen innui nefesh meifer bein
beino le-veina bein beino le-veina ve-acheirim Now here's an important הלכה halakha
which you know might be obvious but we need to be stated,
which is things that are עינוי נפש, innui nefesh, he can annul
whether they focus on their relationship or her relationship with another person.
Let's say for example she says, "I'm not going to like get
any, you know, benefit from any fruit from Michael over there." Now
okay, but it's not the relationship with Michael that matters, the question
is if she doesn't get that fruit will that cause her עינוי
נפש? innui nefesh? Right? So if Michael is the only one that
I don't know, you know, produces apples and we've decided that she
needs apples or everybody needs apples or I don't know what we've
decided, so it doesn't matter that it relates to Michael's fruit, it
matters whether whether not having that will cause her עינוי נפש. innui
nefesh. So if it's about עינוי נפש innui nefesh it doesn't matter
who it's between, who it is, the fact that her being deprived
of that is עינוי נפש. innui nefesh. Okay, so דברים שיש בהן
עינוי נפש devarim she-yesh ba-hen innui nefesh מיפר meifer בין בינו לבינה
בין בינו לבינה ואחרים bein beino le-veina bein beino le-veina ve-acheirim. whether
it related to the two of them, to other people, doesn't matter.
שאין בהם עינוי נפש she-ein ba-hem innui nefesh if it's not a
בין עינוי נפש bein innui nefesh and it's דברים שבינו לבינה, devarim
she-beino le-veina, so then בינו לבינה מיפר beino le-veina meifer בינו לבינה
ואחרים אינו מיפר. beino le-veina ve-acheirim eino meifer. It depends who she's
making the נדר, neder, right? So if she basically says like "I
can't get any benefit from Michael," okay, so you know that might
affect her relationship with Michael but
what does that have to do with you know the husband's relationship
to her? If however she says, "I can't get any benefit from
you," then that affects their dynamics, right? So therefore when it is
something that is objectively about how it affects her עינוי נפש innui
nefesh it doesn't matter what the source of that is. If it's
about the dynamics then it's only to the degree that it relates
to both husband and wife together. Okay, so that should be pretty
clear. Let's see how it gets illustrated. Where are we? We are
on פא עמוד ב, pei aleph amud bet, five lines from the
top, middle of the line כיצד. keitzad. כיצד, keitzad, how is this
true? אמרה קונם פירות אלו עלי amra konam peirot eilu alai
הרי זה יפר. harei ze yafer. If she says I can't get
benefit from fruit, he can annul it and again doesn't matter whose
fruit, her husband's fruit, her own fruit, Michael's fruit, doesn't matter. קונם
שאיני עושה לפי אבא. konam she-eini osa le-fi abba. What?
You might be on. You're on פא עמוד א. pei aleph amud
aleph.
Yes.
Okay. קונם שאיני עושה לפי אבא לפי אחיך. konam she-eini osa le-fi
abba le-fi achicha.
Now let's say it's not even what she can benefit from, you
know, if it affects a relationship that can go either way. So
if she says, "The stuff that I do, my father is אסור
assur to my father, my father can't benefit from any of my
from any of like the labor of my hand." Or you know,
לפי אחיך לפי אביך, le-fi achicha le-fi avicha, your brother, your father,
לפי אחי le-fi achi it can't go into the mouth of my
brother. ושלא אעשה תבן לפני בהמתך ve-she-lo e'ese teven lifnei behemetcha or
I won't, now this sounds more like a שבועה shevua than a
נדר neder but you can find a way to make it a
נדר neder or whatever or the husband can also be מיפר שבועות
meifer shevuot as we learned yesterday, which Michael taught. Thank you, Michael,
for yesterday. Right, שבועות shevuot could also be can also include things
the husband could be מיפר. meifer. So somehow she makes a נדר
neder or a שבועה shevua that she won't give this straw to
the husband's animals, ומים לפני בקרך u-mayim lifnei bekarcha or water to
the cattle. He cannot annul. Now
that's interesting, right? Because you could say it affects his family. I'm
annoyed that you're, that what you're not able to do certain things
for my brother, for my father. You're not able to do things
for my animal. I'm upset at you. You might be upset and
annoyed, but it's not directly about the direct relationship of the two
of you. Okay, and therefore, that is not בינו לבינה. beino leveina.
And since it's not עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, she's not being hurt
by that, so that he cannot annul. Okay, so that's an example
of things that are not עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, that are not
בינו לבינה, beino leveina, affect people other than him, even his immediate
family. He cannot annul.
Doesn't this affect the dynamic in other words?
Right, so you could say that, right?
You're affecting the relationship with my
family, maybe it should be... Exactly. So that's exactly what the חידוש
chiddush here is, that if it affects me, it's the result for
me to be annoyed with you, the wife, but it's not the
נדר neder doesn't directly relate to a thing that's directly between the
two of us, then that actually is considered out of the category.
That's exactly what I think the חידוש chiddush here is, that it
could lead to me being upset, but it's not directly about that
relationship. Okay, now if she says, אינו יכול להפר, eino yachol lehafer,
שלא אכחול ושלא אפרכס ושלא אשמש עם מטתי, shelo ekchol veshelo efarkes
veshelo eshamesh im mitati, if she says I will not put on
makeup, these are different types of makeup, makeup and jewelry, I won't
have sex with you, then יפר. yafer. That he can annul משום
דברים שבינו לבינה mishum dvarim shebeino leveina because that does affect directly
him. Okay, ושלא אציע לך מטתך, veshelo atzia lecha mitatcha, let's say
she says I won't make your bed, ושלא אמזוג לך את הכוס,
veshelo emzog lecha es hakos, I won't mix your wine for you,
ושלא ארחץ לך פניך ידיך ורגליך, veshelo erchatz lecha panecha yadecha veraglecha,
I won't wash your hands and face, אין צריך להפר. ein tzarich
lehafer. He doesn't even have to annul. Why? Even though that clearly
affects their relationship, but because she is obligated to do this for
her husband and one of the things we learn in כתובות Kesubos
is even if a wife brings in a hundred maidservants to do
all of the labor in the house, these things the rabbis mandated
she has to do for her husband because they're basic shows of
intimacy between husband and wife.
Everything except sex
part, though.
Well, obviously sex is the question. Why is it he has to
annul the sex? Because it hurts her own עונה. ono. Right. But
basically this is something that she's already obligated to do and therefore
she doesn't have the power to make it forbidden to the husband.
Okay, so he doesn't even have to annul those. So the דברים
שבינו לבינה dvarim shebeino leveina are a category of things that directly
affect him, but that she is not already obligated to do, because
then it wouldn't even need to be annulled.
And I still think he should annul it anyway.
Well, you've anticipated רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says
יפר. yafer. I agree in principle the way we'll see in the
גמרא, Gemara, but you don't have to annul those, but nevertheless he
should annul those, שנאמר לא יחל דברו, shene'emar lo yachel devaro, he
should not violate his words. So now, what does that tell you
about anything? So the way the רן Ran explains it is he
says it doesn't say לא יחל נדרו lo yachel nidro or שבועתו,
shvuaso, it says דברו. devaro. So the דרשה derashah is even if
it's just a דיבור, dibbur, even if it's just a speech that
really isn't halachically binding, but there's a power of speech and the
fact that those words are out there and they're being ignored is
problematic in the way we think about it. It feels like a
violation, it feels like a disregard of those words. So you should
go through the process, not biblically but rabbinically, of annulling to show
that that speech no longer carries the weight. I'll tell you actually,
I was thinking about this when my son came home from camp
and he basically said, Dad, he said, I got really upset about
the whatever this or that, I took a, I swore dot dot
dot something like that, and he says help me get out of
this. So I said, I said, Well, tell me exactly what happened.
He goes, Well, I said if this whatever, I said, Okay, that's
not a נדר. neder. So whatever the technical stuff was, he says
he wasn't happy. He said, No, you gotta help me here. So
I said, All right, fine, מותר לך מותר לך. mutar lach mutar
lach. He says, Okay, I feel so much
better. So it doesn't matter. Don't tell me it didn't mean anything.
Do something, annul it, get rid of it. Okay.
So all right, fine. Anyway, so that's
what רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says. No, even if it's just words,
you gotta annul it. All right. דבר אחר, davar acher, לא יחל,
lo yachel, now that we're talking about לא יחל דברו, lo yachel
devaro, we have a little digression. לא יחל דברו, lo yachel devaro,
מכאן לחכם שאין מתיר נדרו עצמו, mikan lechacham she'ein matir nidro atzmo,
that you can't annul your own נדר, neder, because it's לא יחל
דברו, lo yachel devaro, we learn from here that you can't be
מתיר matir your נדר, neder, but somebody else can. But you can't
annul your own, turn your own into חולין, chullin, make it go
away.
A prisoner cannot release himself from
jail.
Right, exactly. Okay, so you cannot, you cannot be the person to
be מתיר matir your own נדר. neder. All right. Okay, now, שאין
מתיר נדרו עצמו, she'ein matir nidro atzmo, מאן תנא דאמר? man tana
de'amar? Now why did we bring down this fascinating ברייתא? baraita? Because
we have this discussion of makeup. And remember, what category did he
put makeup in? In the דברים שבינו לבינה, dvarim shebeino leveina, that
when she says she won't put on makeup, that between the two
of them the husband can annul it. So מאן תנא דאמר? man
tana de'amar? מאן שמעת ליה דאמר שלא אכחול ושלא אפקוס דברים שבינו
לבינה הויין, man shama’at lei d’amar shelo echol v’shelo efkos d’varim shebeino
l’veina havyan, that that would be at most things between the two
of them? חזין hazin Rabbi Yose, because remember Rabbi Yose says that,
and I mean the other way of saying it is, why do
we call the makeup in the בינו לבינה? beino l’veina? Makeup according
to the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma is in the עינוי נפש inuy
nefesh category. Remember that? The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says bathing and
makeup is considered like a real self-denial,
and this says it’s not עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh. So who must
it be? It must be Rabbi Yose. Rabbi Yose says it’s not
עינוי נפש, inuy nefesh, and you see what he does say it
is, is בינו לבינה. beino l’veina. So מאן שמעת ליה דאמר שלא
אכחול ושלא אפקוס דברים שבינו לבינה הויין, man shama’at lei d’amar shelo
echol v’shelo efkos d’varim shebeino l’veina havyan, that that would be at
most things between the two of
them? Rabbi Yose. דקא מפר, dik’ka mefer, he can still annul it
משום דברים שבינו לבינה mishum d’varim shebeino l’veina because of things between
the two of them. So that’s a very good proof that even
when Rabbi Yose says bathing and makeup is not עינוי נפש, inuy
nefesh, it still is בינו לבינה beino l’veina because this ברייתא braita
puts makeup in בינו לבינה, beino l’veina, and the only person who
could say that is Rabbi Yose. Okay, so the חכמים Chachamim would
say it’s an issue of עינוי נפש. inuy nefesh.
Very good. Now let’s go back and finish looking at this ברייתא.
braita. אמר מר: amar mar: ושלא אשמש מיטתי יפר משום דברים שבינו
לבינה. v’shelo eshamesh mitati yafer mishum d’varim shebeino l’veina. And if she
says I won’t have sex, then he can annul it because it’s
בינו לבינה. beino l’veina. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute, היכי
דמי? heichi dami? What’s the case? אילימא דאמרה הנאת תשמישי עליך, ilima
d’amrah hana’at tashmishi alecha,
the pleasure of my sex is forbidden to you, so למה לי
הפרה? lamah li hafara? Why does he have to annul it? המשועבדת
ליה. hameshu’abedet leih. She is obligated to him, right? המשועבדת hameshu’abedet also
can be in the sense like he has a lien on her
for this purpose. It’s sort of the other way around, though. What,
she’s obligated to her? No, he’s also. Well, we’ll talk about it
in a minute, it’s both true. Okay, המשועבדת ליה. hameshu’abedet leih.
She’s obligated to him to have sex with him when he wants.
So I
understand, okay, that’s what Michael asks. We’ll get back to that. Anyway,
hold on. Okay, anyway, she cannot make her sex forbidden to her
husband. Okay, it’s not hers to make forbidden or whatever, she has
an obligation, let’s at least put it that way, she has an
obligation, so she can’t make it forbidden to her husband. So that
can’t be. אלא דאמרת, ela d’amrat, הנאת תשמישך עלי. hana’at tashmish’cha alai.
Fine.
What she says is, not you can’t have benefit from having sex
from me, I am forbidding myself to get the pleasure of having
sex from you. Okay? That’s like saying your fruits are forbidden to
me. So she’s allowed to do that in principle, right? She’s not
saying she won’t do her duty to him, she’s saying what you’re
going to give me, the pleasure of having sex with you, that’s
forbidden to me. Now, it just so works out that those two
happen at the same time. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, in
that case, she can, it does take effect, and even though it
indirectly gets in the between sort of undermines her obligation, she’s not
directly doing it. So it’s sort of like when a person says,
I won’t get the benefit of any סוכה. sukkah. I can’t say
all סוכות sukkot are forbidden to me. So it winds up, I
didn’t say I wasn’t going to do the מצוה, mitzvah, I just
said all סוכות sukkot are forbidden to me. Then when it’s time
to do the מצוה, mitzvah, נעבעך, nebech, it’s forbidden to me. So
here too, she didn’t say she wasn’t going to do her obligation
to him, she just said she wouldn’t benefit from him. But then
when it comes time for her to do her obligation, she can’t
be forced to do it because then she’ll be put in a
position of doing a transgression. Okay? So,
אלא דאמרת
כרב כהנא, ela d’amrat k’Rav Kahana, like Rav Kahana. דאמר רב כהנא,
d’amar Rav Kahana, because Rav Kahana says: הנאת תשמישי עליך, hana’at tashmishi
alecha, if a woman says the pleasure of my sex is forbidden
to you,
כופין ומשמשתו. kofin u’meshamshto. She has to go ahead and have sex
with him. הנאת תשמישך עלי, hana’at tashmish’cha alai, if she says the
pleasure of your sex is forbidden to me, then יפר, yafer, then
he has to annul it. Why? Because that does take effect. Why
does it take effect? שאין מאכילין את אדם דבר האסור לו, she’ein
ma’achilin et adam davar ha’asur lo, that even though he has a
duty of sex with her, that doesn’t override the fact that now
this is forbidden, right? That’s like it’s a טריפה treifa thing to
her. You can’t force her to eat something טריפה. treifa. You can’t
force the sex on her if it’s now something that’s forbidden to
her. So therefore indirectly it got in the way of her doing
her obligation, but because it wasn’t direct, it took effect. Because it
affects their dynamic, he’s in a position to annul. Now, a couple
of you, two of you asked: isn’t it his obligation to have
sex with her and not hers to his? But as we learn
through כתובות, Ketubot, the גמרא Gemara takes it for granted that even
without the פסוק pasuk of עונה, onah, takes it for granted that
a wife has to have sex with her husband. A wife who
refuses to have sex with her husband is called in הלכה, halacha,
מורדת, moredet, a rebel. Okay? Which by the way, for רמב"ם Rambam
became a basis of dealing with the גט get and עגונה agunah
problem, which became something in the רמב"ם Rambam in the time of
the רמב"ם Rambam basically women who couldn’t get a גט, get, couldn’t
get divorced from their husband, basically just inverted to Islam and were
freed from their marriage. So רמב"ם Rambam had to solve the problem.
So רמב"ם Rambam basically says, if a woman says that I no
longer love my husband, I find him I can’t tolerate him and
I refuse to have sex with him, that the רמב"ם Rambam says
we say that that’s legitimate.
And therefore, and since the marriage isn't tolerable anymore, therefore you force
the man to give a גט. Get. So how's that anyway? So
that's interesting in terms of that. But the הלכה halakha is that
the גמרא Gemara says that a woman who refuses to have sex
with her husband is called a מורדת, moredet, a rebel. Where does
that obligation come from? So the רשב"א Rashba wants to sort of
see that that's a natural part of marriage. The way the רשב"א
Rashba says it is when husband and wife stand up, it's like
he doesn't quote any פסוק, pasuk, but he just says when they
go to the חופה chuppah to get married, he says this is
why they're getting married, that they should have part of what marriage
is, it's not just a contract, it's basically a commitment to have
sexual fidelity and to be and to have sex with one another.
So therefore he says that that's like just an implicit part of
what the marriage is, that they're משועבד meshubad one to the other
to have sex. Now does that mean on demand, even if the
other person doesn't want it? Okay, that's a different point. Presumably not,
presumably within certain reasonable limits, right? But as anybody knows who's within
a marriage, it's like it's not always like sometimes one person is
more into it than the other, so it depends how much the
other person is, there's that part of the negotiation within a marriage
in terms of figuring out how to accommodate the other person if
it's within your sort of ability. But anyway, but that's the way
the רשב"א Rashba says. He says that's like that's implicit in the
contract of marriage. רמב"ם Rambam says what might be a more פשט
pshat but is obviously more problematic, because he basically says that that's
what the קנין kinyan of קידושין kiddushin is about. We'll discuss this
when we get to קידושין. kiddushin. The קידושין kiddushin is a sense
of acquisition. Money is paid, there's essentially that means, like the רמב"ם
Rambam says more this הלכה, halakha, but it's like explained by the
נצי"ב Netziv and anyway it's implicit in the רמב"ם, Rambam, that the
woman is basically like sexual property of the man. So therefore the
way the רמב"ם Rambam says why she can't take a vow to
say having sex with her is forbidden is not just because she
has an obligation to have sex with him. He says because it's
not hers to make forbidden. It's like trying to make somebody else's
fruit forbidden on you, it's her husband, her husband owns that as
it were. Now that is a reason that's problematic not just ideologically,
it's because that if that approach can lead to and justify marital
rape.
Which is what, what about כופה? kofeh?
כופה, kofeh, right. So I glossed over what the word כופה kofeh
means. So כופה, kofeh, כופה kofeh could be like physically force, or
כופה kofeh could just be like tough luck, you have no choice,
you have to, it sort of mean we legally demand it. So
that's always the question. כופה kofeh does sometimes mean that, but it's
questionable, you're right, what כופה kofeh means. And there definitely are cases
about women that came to rabbis to say my husband is forcing
me to have sex, and the rabbi said like I can't help
you, like you're,
he owns you for that purpose. I mean whether they used that
language or not. Okay. Now again, they're not always. There was a
whole history of how הלכה's halakha dealt with marital, marital rape. Okay,
but anyway, so that's part of what's going on there.
But obviously you've got
to get around it
by saying the הנאה hana'ah of your תשמיש.
tashmish. Yeah, well that was the way you'd make it forbidden. Whether
a woman who was feeling, whether the husband would have cared about
that, the same husband that's raping his wife, I don't know. All
right. Now let's just read one more sentence. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, מן תנא הדיתניא? Man tana hadetanya? Who is the
תנא tana of that ברייתא baraita which we taught? דברים המותרים ואחרים
נהגו בהן איסור, אי אתה רשאי לנהוג בהן היתר כדי לבטלן. Devarim
hamutarim ve'acheirim nahagu bahen issur, ee ata rashai linhog bahen heiter kedei
levatlam. If something is really permissible but people have a practice of
treating it forbidden,
you can't just say, "Hey, you guys are crazy, this is really
מותר," muttar, and start acting in a way that sort of in
defiance of their practice. You can't be dismissive of their thing. משום
שנאמר mishum shenemar because it says לא יחל דברו, Lo yachel devaro,
do not let their words become violated. Now again this is sort
of in the line with what we said over רבן גמליאל, Rabban
Gamliel, which is even if it's not technically a נדר, neder, right?
Which is a question, do certain like religious מנהגים minhagim become נדרים?
nedarim? But the way this is being read, the simple way is,
it might not technically be a נדר, neder, but the same way
you don't like just ignore words, you treat them respectfully even if
they're not technically a נדר, neder, if people are treating this practice
seriously, you don't just, you're not just dismissive of it. You don't
just, right? So even if it's not really binding religiously הלכתית halakhically
as a נדר neder etc., don't just be dismissive of it. דרש
פה לא יחל דברו, מכאן לחכם שאין מיפר נדרי עצמו. Derash pe
lo yachel devaro, mikan lachacham she'ein meifer nidrei atzmo. What we said
before, you can't annul your own. Who is that? רבן גמליאל. Rabban
Gamliel. Oh yeah, that's רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel both because it has
the דבר אחר davar acheir and also because it's a similar idea.
Even if something is not technically a נדר, neder, you don't just
completely throw it out and dismiss it. One last point about the
נדרי עצמו nidrei atzmo is the interesting question of can somebody be
מתיר matir his wife's נדרים? nedarim? And the ר"ן Ran raises this
question and he basically says מתיר matir versus
מיפר, meifer, מתיר, matir, right? So he basically says to the degree
that the husband is
a, is
an interested party. If you're a נוגע בדבר. nogea badavar. Okay. So
if my התרה hatara of my wife's נדר neder somehow impacts me,
it's not בין לו לבינה, bein lo l'veina, right? Or it's בין
לו לבינה bein lo l'veina but it's more than twenty-four hours, whatever
the case might be, then I can't do it because I'm a
because I have a I have a vested interest. But if it
doesn't affect me, can I do it? That actually is a debate
in a משנה mishna which רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma and presumably it has to do with a type
of like an אשתו כגופו ishto k'gufo type of a question. So
even though קרובים krovim are okay, right, אשתו כגופו ishto k'gufo you
can't do your own, and then the question becomes a man doing
for his wife as התרת נדרים hatarat nedarim and that's an open
question. I think there's a מחלוקת machloket of even how we פוסק
pasken on that. Okay? And we'll end with that for today.